A step-by-step Guide to Postgres Database Upgrade(Postgres 9.5 to Postgres 10.0)

1.Make a backup of the exiting database(s). Make sure that your database is not being updated 
>pg_dumpall > existing_databases.*(sql, tar, zip)

2.Install Postgres 10 (https://wwww.postgresql.org/download/linux/ubuntu/)
>Then run sudo apt-get install postgresql-10. a newer version will be installed side by side with the earlier version.

3.Run pg_lsclusters:
>Ver Cluster Port Status Owner    Data directory               Log file
>9.6 main    5432 online postgres /var/lib/postgresql/9.6/main /var/log/postgresql/postgresql-9.6-main.log

>10  main    5433 online postgres /var/lib/postgresql/10/main  /var/log/postgresql/postgresql-10-main.log

>There already is a cluster main for 10 (since this is created by default on package installation). This is done so that a fresh installation works out of the box without the need to create a cluster first, but of course it clashes when you try to upgrade 9.6/main when 10/main also exists. The recommended procedure is to remove the 10 cluster with pg_dropcluster and then upgrade with pg_upgradecluster.

4.Stop the 10 cluster and drop it:

>sudo pg_dropcluster 10 main --stop

5.Stop all processes and services writing to the database. Stop the database:

>sudo systemctl stop postgresql

6.Upgrade the 9.6 cluster:

>sudo pg_upgradecluster -m upgrade 9.6 main

7.Start PostgreSQL again

>sudo systemctl start postgresql

8.Run pg_lsclusters. Your 9.6 cluster should now be "down", and the 10 cluster should be online at 5432:

>Ver Cluster Port Status Owner    Data directory               Log file
>9.6 main    5433 down   postgres /var/lib/postgresql/9.6/main /var/log/postgresql/postgresql-9.6-main.log
>10  main    5432 online postgres /var/lib/postgresql/10 

9.First, check that everything works fine. After that, remove the 9.6 cluster:
>sudo pg_dropcluster 9.6 main --stop

Note: If you have a really big cluster, you may use pg_upgradecluster with a --link option, so that the upgrade will be in-place. However, this is dangerous — you can lose the cluster in an event of failure. Just don't use this option if not necessary, as -m upgrade is already fast enough.




